"What I Will"
"ماذا سأفعل"
I will not dance to your war drum.
انا لن أرقص على وقع طبول حربك
I will not lend my soul nor my bones to your war drum.
ولن احني جسدي ولا روحي .. لطبول حربك
I will not dance to that beating.
ولن ارقص لهذا الضرب
I know that beat.
أعرف ان الضرب
It is lifeless.
لا إنساني
I know intimately that skin you are hitting.
انا اعرف ان الجلد الذي تضربه
It was alive once,
كان على قيد الحياة ذات يوم
hunted, stolen,
تم اصطياده .. سرقته ..
stretched.
تمديده
I will not dance to your drummed-up war.
انا لن أرقص على وقع طبول حربك
I will not pop, spin, break for you.
انا لن اغني .. اشتم .. احطم من اجلك
I will not hate for you
انا لن اكره من اجلك
or even hate you.
ولن اكرهك
I will not kill for you.
انا لن اقتل من اجلك
Especially I will not die for you.
وحتماً لن اموت من اجلك
I will not mourn the dead with murder nor suicide.
انا لن اندب القتلى .. ولا المنتحرين
I will not side with you or dance to bombs
انا لن اقف بصفك .. ولن ارقص على دوي القنابل
because everyone is dancing.
لان الجميع يريد الرقص
Everyone can be wrong.
فالجميع يمكن ان يكون على خطأ
Life is a right, not collateral or casual.
الحياة محقة .. ليست تراكمية .. وليست محض صدفة
I will not forget where I come from.
انا لن انسى من أين أتيت
I will craft my own drum.
سوف اصنع طبلتي الخاصة
Gather my beloved near,
وسوف اجمع احبائي بقربي
and our chanting will be dancing.
وسوف نرقص على انغامنا
Our humming will be drumming.
ان دمدمتنا .. سوف تصبح نغماً نرقص عليه
I will not be played.
انا لن اسمح لكم بالتلاعب بي
I will not lend my name nor my rhythm to your beat.
انا لن اعير اسمي .. او صوتي ..لك لكي تقتل فيه
I will dance and resist and dance and persist and dance.
انا سوف ارقص واعترض .. وارقص واتظاهر .. وارقص
This heartbeat is louder than death.
ان دقات قلبي وقعها اكبر من الموت
Your war drum ain't louder
ان طبول حربك منخفضة الصوت
than this breath. Haaa.
صوتها خافت اقل من صوت الهمس .. هااا .
What's up TED people? Let me hear you make some noise.
كيف حالكم اعضاء " تيد " ؟ دعوني اسمع صوتكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A bunch of pacifists.
يا رعاة السلام
Confused, aspiring pacifists.
ايها المشوشون .. الملهمون .. يا رعاة السلام
I understand.
انا اعي
I've been wrong a lot lately.
انني كنت مخطئة كثيراً
Like a lot.
كثيراً حقاً
So I couldn't figure out
ولم اكن اعي مالذي يجب ان اقرأه
what to read today.
اليوم لكم
I mean, I've been saying I've been prepping.
اعني .. كنت اعد نفسي ..
What that means is prepping my outfit,
ولكن في الحقيقة كنت اعد ملابسي فحسب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
prepping options,
اعددت الخيارات
trying to figure out what I'm coming behind
وكنت اجمع الافكار التي اريد طرحها
and going in front of.
وتلك التي اريد اغفالها
Poetry does that.
ان العشر هكذا
It preps you. It aims you.
انه يحضرك .. انه يستهدفك
So I am going to read a poem
لذا سوف أقرأ لكم قصيدة
that was chosen just now.
اخترها الآن فحسب
But I'm going to need you
ولكن انا احتاج اليكم
to just sit for like 10 minutes
لكي تجلسوا .. نحو 10 دقائق
and hold a woman who is not here.
وان تستحضروا فتاة ليست موجودة هنا
Hold her now
استحضروها الآن
with you.
معكم
You don't need to say her name out loud, you can just hold her.
لا يتوجب عليكم ان تخبرونا باسمها .. فقط تذكروها
Are you holding her?
هل هي موجودة الآن
This is "Break Clustered."
هذه هي " العناقيد المتكسرة "
All holy history banned.
كل التاريخ المقدس محجوب
Unwritten books predicted the future, projected the past.
كتب لم تكتب تنبأت بالمستقبل .. فهمت الماضي
But my head unwraps
عقلي بدأ يرى
around what appears limitless,
ما يتجاوز الحدود
man's creative violence.
وعنف الانسان المبدع
Whose son shall it be?
نتاج من هذا ؟
Which male child will perish a new day?
من هو الطفل الذي يعدم اليوم الجديد ؟
Our boys' deaths galvanize.
كثرت اعداد وفيات الاطفال
We cherish corpses.
وكثر تقديس الموت
We mourn women, complicated.
نحن ننتحب على النساء .. انه امرٌ معقد
Bitches get beat daily.
ان بائعات الهوى يضربن كل يوم
Profits made, prophets ignored.
الرسل .. تخرج .. الرسل تُهمل
War and tooth, enameled salted lemon childhoods.
الحروب .. كما الاسنان اللبنية ..
All colors run, none of us solid.
كلها تختفي بعد حين ..
Don't look for shadow behind me. I carry it within.
لاتنظروا الى الشبح الذي احمله في داخلي
I live cycles of light and darkness.
انا اعيش في دوائر من الضوء والعتمة
Rhythm is half silence.
ان السجع نصف الصمت
I see now, I never was one and not the other.
انا ارى اليوم .. انا لم اكن شخصاً آخر يوما ما
Sickness, health, tender violence.
الموت .. الصحة .. العنف
I think now I never was pure.
انا افكر اليوم .. انا لست نقية كما اظن
Before form I was storm,
قبل التشكل .. كنت عاصفة
blind, ign'ant -- still am.
هوجاء عمياء .. وانا كذلك اليوم
Human contracted itself blind, malignant.
ان الانسان يسير مغلق العينين
I never was pure.
انا لست نقية كما اظن
Girl spoiled before ripened.
ان البنات يُفسدن بالدلال .. فلا ينضجن
Language can't math me.
اللغة لا تستطيع التعبير عني
I experience exponentially.
لقد خضت التجربة مراراً
Everything is everything.
كل شيء .. هو كل شيء
One woman loses 15, maybe 20, members of her family.
بعض النساء فقدن 15 , 20 شخصاً من افراد عائلتها
One woman loses six.
والبعض فقدن 6
One woman loses her head.
والبعض فقدن رأسهن
One woman searches rubble. One woman feeds on trash.
والبعض تبحث في القمامة .. والبعض تأكل منها
One woman shoots her face. One woman shoots her husband.
والبعض يُقتلن بطلقة في الرأس .. والبعض يَقتلن ازواجهن
One woman straps herself.
البعض يخلعن ملابسهن
One woman gives birth to a baby.
والبعض ينجبن الاطفال
One woman gives birth to borders.
والبعض ينجبن الحدود
One woman no longer believes love will ever find her.
والبعض فقدن الامل في ايجاد الحب
One woman never did.
والبعض لا يجدنه
Where do refugee hearts go?
اين تذهب قلوب اللاجئين
Broken, dissed,
كيف تتحطم .. تتسمم
placed where they're not from, don't want to be missed.
كيف تنفى الى اماكن بعيدة .. دون ان يفتقدها احد
Faced with absence.
وكأنها مفقودة غائبة
We mourn each one
نحن ننتحب لاجل بعضنا البعض
or we mean nothing at all.
وننتحب لاننا لا نعني شيئاً في النهاية
My spine curves spiral.
نحن في دوامة تشابه فقرات عمودي الفقري
Precipice running to and running from human beings.
ان الانسان يدفع نفسه الى الهاوية
Cluster bombs left behind.
القنابل العنقودية ترمى
De facto landmines.
الالغام الارضية تزرع
A smoldering grief.
الحزن ينتشر
Harvest contaminated tobacco.
المحاصيل تمتلىء بالتوباكوا
Harvest bombs.
والناس تحصد قنابل تقتل فيها
Harvest baby teeth.
يحصدون الاطفال
Harvest palms, smoke.
يحصدون راحات اليد .. يحصدون الدخان
Harvest witness, smoke.
دخان الحقيقة
Resolutions, smoke.
دخان الحلول
Salvation, smoke.
دخان الاستعباد
Redemption, smoke.
دخان الخلاص
Breathe.
تنفس
Do not fear
لا تخف
what has blown up.
من ذلك الدخان
If you must,
ان اردت
fear the unexploded.
ان تخف .. فخف من ذلك الدخان الذي لم ينفث بعد
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)